The interaction patterns in software
will totally change with agents. A lot
of the agents are chat interfaces. They
are kind of giving you an answer. My
view on it is that it will be more like
an interactive mode between the user and
the agent. As an example, today I'm
using Google presentation and there is
this nano banana feature. The result is
pretty disappointing because it creates
an image out of your presentation. I
think the way you want it as a user is
that I say, "Hey, help me make my
presentation slide nicer." And then I
can still go in and change the size or
the text. Before OTel, every vendor,
including myself as Instana, did their
own format. And OpenTelemetry actually
was the first approach to standardize
this format. If you look at a lot of
vendors, they say, "We support
OpenTelemetry." What that means is that
you can send them OpenTelemetry data.
They take that data and convert it into
their internal format. What we have
built is the data is always
OpenTelemetry because all the models by
default understand the format and
therefore can really work with it
similar to what they can do with code.
>> How do you think about the career path
in sort of software engineering today?
And what's a good thing for someone to
do today if they're sort of early in
their career? Yeah, so um
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So, whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
A really quick ask, 90% of people who
are listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. All
right, back to the episode.
Hello everyone. Welcome back to the AI
Native Dev. Today, we're going to go
plunging deep into the world of of
DevOps and observability and you know,
what does that look like in the world of
AI? And to dig into that, we have Mirko
Novakovic, who was the founder of
Instana, so this built an observability
platform, sold it to to IBM. That's
where we met Mirko way back then. And
and today is the founder and CEO of Dash
Zero, building that out. So Mirko,
thanks for coming on to the show.
Yeah, thanks for having me.
So just to dig in, start by giving us a
bit of context of like Dash Zero, the
company you're you've built and are
running today. Tell us a few words about
it and and some of its core.
Yeah, so
we are an AI native observability
platform.
We actually started when we started
we were not
promoting AI native at the beginning. We
were open telemetry native. And that
turned out to be a good foundation for
AI by the way, which we can discuss, but
So the idea was there is a new standard
in observability called open telemetry,
which standardizes the format of the
telemetry data, unlocks metric traces,
end user events,
and also standardizes the tagging system
on that telemetry data, which is called
the semantic convention. So
post name now is host underscore name or
host.name. And
that that is the way we have started. So
we built a full platform for logs,
traces, metric, end user monitoring,
taking only open telemetry data into it
and keeping it as open telemetry and
making the most out of the semantic
convention by creating context. So if
you look at a trace, you see all the
logs, you see the metrics, the
underlying infrastructure, everything in
context based on the semantic
convention. And we try to make a very
easy onboarding flow, PLG type of
uh sales motion and and having it
easy to use.
Yeah, so so part of it is is kind of
just a an extra end observability
platform that sort of gives you all the
tools and then always kind of combines
all this sort of
uh the the broadened scope of what what
observability captures today with the
you know traces and logs and and and all
that jazz. Uh but I think that core of
open open telemetry or Otel is really
interesting. Uh I I guess maybe you can
sort of say a few words about Otel
itself and its distinction between what
is it when is it a format and when is it
fields, right? Because I know when when
Open Telemetry came came around, there
was a lot of uh
maybe like a a first set of companies
that sort of built on top of it and were
maybe overly optimistic at not just the
format but like the type of information
that would just magically I'll just
connect to the system and they already
have Otel, I will have the info I need
and they learned not all the information
is always there. Um
but but some did standardize. So, maybe
can you say a bit of a like what have
you seen in terms of Open Telemetry?
Where has it standardized just formats
and what data
is is sort of typical to find in any any
Otel based uh
kind of capture?
Yeah, it's um so, let's start by why why
I think it's also meaningful, right?
Before Otel,
it is every vendor, including myself as
Instana, did their own format, right?
So, we had an agent and so you specified
your own format and you sent your own
format to the
>> This is the tracing agent, not an AI
agent. E- exactly. That's the old school
agent that you install on your host,
basically, and that captures the data,
right? The CPU utilization, the logs,
and and the traces. Exactly, it's not an
AI agent. The benefit was that you could
make everything you needed for your
platform, right? In into the format and
you could do do some automatics. So, for
example, if the agent was running on the
host, you could add the host name
because you were running on it and just
send it over, right? Um and Open
Telemetry actually was the first
approach to standardize
this um this format, right? So, that you
have no proprietary data and the and and
I think the main drivers were the cloud
providers
because if you're running something like
AWS Lambda or any managed service and
you want to provide
telemetry data of that service, how do
you do that, right? You either provide
it in 20 formats like Data Dog, New
Relic, Datadog
or you have a standardized format that
everybody can understand. And that's how
it started, right? So, I would also say
if you look at a lot of vendors, they
say we we support open telemetry.
What that means is that you can send
them open telemetry data, but I would
say still 90% of the vendors, they take
that data and convert it into their
internal format. Right.
>> Because that's how the platform is
built. So, you can send it, but then in
the system
essentially they they they the tagging
system etc. is gone, right? Because it's
now
Data Dog format or uh format of any
other vendor, right? And I think uh what
we have built is something where it the
the data is always open telemetry. It
stays open telemetry. Right.
>> is still open telemetry in the tool.
And uh yeah, coming back to your
question, I think there's only one tag
that is mandatory
and that's service name.
Okay. So, the only tag the the only tag
in and and so essentially everything
that emits telemetry data is a service,
right? In in in that in that that sense.
And so, if you have a service, I don't
know, a payment service and you send a
log, you add the service.name equals
payment service. Yeah.
>> And if you have a metric of that, you do
the same and now you can correlate
everything on a service level by saying
give me all the metrics, logs, traces
Right.
>> service name.
Yeah, that's that's the only thing
that's mandatory and that's also that's
also a bit of a problem I would say for
vendors because we also see that a lot
of the data we get from customers at the
beginning does not have all the
information that would be needed. For
example, if you now ask give me all the
logs of that pod or that host
if that log does not have the pod name
and the host name as a tag, we can't do
it, right? Because
again, going back to proprietary agents,
there we could add that information to
the
log or
ourselves, but now we are relying on the
customer sending us the right context
and if we don't get that context, we
can't
really
recreate it, right? So,
there are companies like Ali Garden are
only focusing on quality of telemetry
data, right? They actually look at data
and then they will tell you, "Oh, by the
way, here we see it's running
Kubernetes, but we are missing the
Kubernetes cluster name and the pod name
and and so we can give you hints of
doing doing better, right?
By the way, I think there is also a big
chance for AI.
We could actually look at data and then
proactively
add configuration data or add
>> Populate kind of those fields. But this
is a but it's a bit of an inverted
version which is the sort of the core of
it is say
whoever it is that is operating the
system,
they they have metadata that they store
on top of it instead of having that
metadata be extracted or inferred or
captured in the observability system or
in an external system otherwise
monitoring
those services, you
you you kind of collaborate or sort of
push the customer, help them more
relevant, maybe AI does that more and
and populate that information at the
source, you know, to sort of decorate
the services with the right uh Exactly.
We we for example also built an open
source project, a Kubernetes operator.
And uh by using that operator, we do all
that configuration stuff for you. So, if
you use that operator, we will
essentially make sure that all the
telemetry data has the right Kubernetes
information, host information set. And
we also auto-inject the agents
the agents, for example, to Java or
Node.js into your runtimes on the fly,
right? So, that you get all this And the
word is confusing word right now. Like
again, these are agents. These are not
the AI agents. These are the uh
observability agents. The sort of the
instrumentation agents of the AI.
Yeah, you really like wait, I don't know
how we got ourselves in this trouble,
but uh
today in observability, you definitely
have a ambiguity around the the word
agent. Or in security, right? Yeah.
That's true as well. So, and so I mean
at this point, listeners might be a
little bit like, isn't this an AI
startup? And an AI podcast, you know,
like what what's going on here? So, you
know, you you mentioned that OTel proved
actually kind of quite useful
when it came to agents. Like tell us a
bit more about that. Like why
why was it useful? It was useful. I I
think it started by when when these LLMs
came out and we started experimenting
with it that we saw that we get really
good results with those with those uh
platforms like
uh uh
uh Claude, for example. We use Claude
internally giving us really good results
by saying, "Hey, analyze this trace,
right?" And we put in a trace, which is
literally a text format of tags, right?
Which is specified by OpenTelemetry. And
now the thing is because it is actually
open source, it's openly documented,
it's an open standard, all these models
are trained on the data, and they
literally understand that host.name is a
host name, and they can start uh
basically understanding the context,
getting what is uh HTTP status code 404.
You then know that it's actually a
problem, right? And now it can really
analyze these things. So, OpenTelemetry
turned out to be really useful because
all the models by default understand the
format, understand OpenTelemetry, and
therefore can really work with it
similar to what they can do with code,
right? Right. It's like it's a text
structure, text format, very well
specified. It has a syntax, it has
semantics, and so it it can actually
really do interesting things and analyze
Yeah.
telemetry data. Uh
I mean, we were really impressed by the
output, right?
And this is a this is still uh format
oriented, right? Because there isn't I
don't know at least of any
um kind of big bodies of
uh telemetry data, even OpenTelemetry
data, that are just available for the
LLMs to to train on. Generally, I think
in the world of DevOps, like traces, you
know, what everything you collect even
in Dash 0,
it's in your system. It's not published
anywhere, unlike maybe like GitHub for
code.
>> published. There are a few repositories
where you can find a large amount of
logs and and spans uh uh as examples,
right? Yeah. Uh by the By the way, once
they tested it, is it like what what
they custom created or is it like
donated logs, you know, from a Donated.
It's kind of donated, yes. It's kind of
donated. And by the way, a funny funny
story is when we started, there is a
OpenTelemetry sample application,
also open source, and the sample
application has very well documented
problems in it, right?
>> Right.
>> Different of errors. And when we started
with LLMs, we asked the LLMs about
problems in that sample application
because it was running, and it always
gave us perfect answers.
And we were super excited at the
beginning, but it turned out the LLM was
also trained with the problems
documented
>> Yeah. on the actual list, so it could do
it because it
It could cheat the test because it knew
the problems up front, right? So, so
results were the amazing at the
beginning, but then we figured out,
okay, it's actually not that amazing
with other things. And then we kind of
connected the dots that it was already
trained on the documentation of the
problems, right? So, um
So, I guess
drilling into that a little bit. So,
like the the LLMs were naturally better,
you know, that was like a nice a nice
kind of benefit of choosing open
technologies that the LLMs
came pre-made or pre-ready
to to process open telemetry data. Is it
that they're not very good at analyzing
traces? They're not very good at like
understanding time series data? They
don't
you know, the the volume of data a
little bit is there. I guess it has
>> Yeah.
On on those fronts like OTel no OTel,
like that doesn't terribly matter,
right? Or like I guess what has been
your experience in terms of like the the
native support of like just drop this
trace in
into whatever Claude or
ChatGPT and and get some result.
I think there are two separate problems,
right? One is you have one phrase and
there is a problem in it, right? An
erroneous span or something. If you do
if you do drop that trace into, for
example, Claude, I think it will
definitely come up with an analysis tell
you, "Hey, I see there's a problem with
this trace." And depending on the
metadata it gets, for example, it's a
database problem and it gets gets a
database status code in there from an
Oracle database, it will
look up that
error code and will give you context on
that error. So, they are really good at
saying, "Hey, this is actually, I don't
know, exhaustion of a connection pool in
the Oracle database and you should do
this and that based on the
documentation." This is essentially what
you would do as a human, right? You you
would see that code and then search for
it. And it does the job for you. Where
it is not really good if you have
thousands or millions of traces to
figure out anomalies instead of A
because the they they can't really do
that large amount of data, right? The
volume. So, what you have to do there is
you have to provide the agent with you
build now we are talking about the AI
agent. Yeah.
>> You have to give the AI agent the right
tools
to do the analysis, right? So, we have a
functionality for example called triage.
What triage does it it compares you give
it a million
traces and ask is there any anomaly in
it for erroneous traces and it would
look at all the
um tags and would tell you, "Oh, the the
the ones with the error always have this
customer ID
as uh uh
as as a tag." And then it would return
that result. And now we provide that
tool to the agent
through an MCP server, right? And the
agent can now the AI agent can now use
that tool that triage tool
and it will use it, right? Autonomously.
It will say, "Okay, there's a problem.
Let's figure out if there are any
anomalies. So, let's use that triage
feature." So, yes, you have to build
your API essentially in a way that it
works for the agent and that the agent
can use it. Yeah. Yeah, to be consumed.
So, I think maybe let's uh delineate.
So, we want to talk a little bit about
sort of
the the the way in which AI meets uh you
know, observability uh needs and so
forth, that type of analysis. And I
think there are sort of three uh uh
pillars here to to talk about. One is,
you know, what we started talking about
here, which is more the kind of AI
power. Like how do you how do you use AI
to an agent to to to be smarter, right?
To sort of you know, offload more of
that work, provide good functionality.
The second is about agent as a consumer.
Uh and you know, I think you started now
talking about the agent will consume.
So, I want to disambiguate a little bit
of which agent is that? Is it your agent
or is it like client's agent? And then
maybe we go a little bit more
philosophical, talk about sort of
product and talk about scope and uh
and the likes. Um so, maybe maybe let's
start so we started, you know, like
digging a lot more like the other ones
can do this, it can't do that. Uh, so
why don't we talk like you have a bunch
of agent powered observability. Um, I
don't know how you call them. I'll let
you say that in a second. Under the
under the mantle of agent zero uh, is
the capabilities. Um, so tell us about
that. Like what are what what is what
are useful things to do today with AI
when it comes to to this world? I mean,
there's when we started agent zero was
just one AI agent, but then over time we
figured out that there are actually a
lot of use cases where where AI agents
make sense. And now agent zero is just a
platform for agents and we have
different ones. And I think the most
prominent in the whole space, there's
also a category AI SRE agents, is
essentially troubleshooting, right? I
mean, you you get a call 3:00 a.m. in
the morning, there's an outage, you have
a problem, and now you want AI to
support you figuring out what the
problem is, right? And and it turns out
they're actually pretty good at it. So,
that's that's the SRE agent. We call him
that agent the seeker.
So, it's an agent we give every name
every agent a name, and so that's the
seeker, and the seeker is essentially
the troubleshooting agent that helps you
with any kind of problem figuring out in
the data what the root cause of the
problem is. Right. So, it would tell And
this is I guess the the
the the root of the root cause analysis
uh,
agent, is it mostly about sort of
discovering the data? Is more about
analysis? I guess what would you say are
are the sort of the
the core competencies of that agent? I
think it must do both, right? First, it
must understand the underlying system
and the dependencies because it's the
agent literally has to figure out where
to look at, right? Yeah. Uh, and and and
then it's about
digging into the data and figuring out
if if if it's a log or a span or a
metric that is the root cause of the
problem of there's any correlation,
right? So, it's a step of things, right?
Normally, you would see the agent
figuring, okay, which service affected
of the problem and what is the
underlying infrastructure and then it
would ask our server, give me the spans
and logs, the erroneous logs of that
service and give me the CPU time of that
underlying Kubernetes pod. And so, it
gathers all the data, analyzes it and
and tries to narrow it down, right? So,
that's that's essentially how these RCA
root cause analysis agents work. And
again, it they work pretty well, right?
Because most of the errors are
text-based and and
it's it's easy for an agent to
look at the data and figure out what to
do next. Yeah, I think the domains that
are sort of getting the most success are
sort of the very text-heavy domains and
this one definitely qualifies there. I I
how do you think about like you build
your agent? I'm sort of breaking my own
sort of ordering there of the of the
pillars and the
of it, but you know, you talk about
building your own agent, you're
describing a sequence of actions. I can
imagine, you know, Claude code or like
any sort of other agent that I have
myself going off and using tools to do
these things and get the right steering.
I guess how do you think about
building your own agent versus
integrating into into whoever it is that
the customer has an agent, you know, why
why have your own and and do you think
that's a long-term or short-term
reality?
It's something I'm not 100% sure of
how how it will work. So, we do both,
right? We integrate into agents like
Claude code or cursor or whatever
through our MCP server. So, there the
use case is or the idea is the
developers inside of the IDE is
centrally it's cursor or something. And
now they can ask a question, figure out
the errors of that service in
production, and suggest me fixes in
code, right? So, it will connect to our
MCP server, do the analysis that we that
we just discussed, narrow it down,
can then use
uh the the functionality of cursor to
match it with the right code, and see if
it could suggest a a fix in the code,
right? I think that's
that's a natural kind of uh use case for
developer. Or what why would the
developer lock into a second tool? Why
wouldn't you stay inside of the tool,
right? So, that's one sort of
integration. But then there's the other
use case that
uh you get a Slack message or a
PagerDuty message, uh and it says, "Hey,
uh we have a higher error rate on your
payment service." And you want to click
on it and get a full analysis in context
of the data, right? With the dashboards,
with the spans, with the logs, you want
to analyze it. And there the agent is
inside of our tool. That's that's the
agent zero then. And it it will guide
you
through the UI, right? And I I'm I'm
just off a meeting with my product team
because I do think that
uh this is something we we are working
on right now, that the interaction
patterns in in software will totally
change with agents, right? I think at
the moment we are still at the beginning
where a lot of the agents are chat
interfaces, and and they are kind of
giving you an answer.
My view on it is that it will be more
like an interactive mode between the
user and the agent, right? Right. Um as
an example, today I'm using Google
presentation,
and there is this nano banana feature,
which says, "Hey, do you want me to
update your slides?"
And I think the result is pretty
disappointing because the result is that
it creates an image out of your
presentation. And now the slide is an
image. It is nice because it looks like
but now it's not interactable anymore
for me as a user, right?
>> editing it yourself, you know, you
>> Exactly. And I think the way you want it
as a user is that I say, "Hey, help me
make my presentation slide nicer." And
then I can still go in and change the
size or the text, right? And that's the
same for us. At the moment, the agent
will tell you this and that is the root
cause. Yeah. But may what you really
want is I think that it will show you it
will actually do the filtering and
everything inside of the tool, will
pinpoint it and now as a user you can
say, "Yeah, but I remove this error and
now do the analysis again, right?"
Because I know that this problem is not
really the problem. So,
it's it's more an interactive mode,
right? I think that's something I really
we are creating right now. So, at the
moment we are still at this nano banana
type of integration, right? It's it's
nice, but I don't think it's the final
way
we want to see inter-
more as an interactive mode, right?
>> Which encoding you already have, right?
It creates code, you cannot change the
code.
>> Yeah. Although even yeah, and even
though there's kind of the conversation
right now for instance on the sort of
the IDE versus versus the sort of the
terminal base, you know, what is what is
the preferred path on it. But it sounds
like you're dividing it into, you know,
the the maybe the sort of the lowest
level is the tools. It's just the
ability to
kind of access different parts of the
system. That's probably just your APIs
and you have the MCPs on top of that
sounds like some sort of analytical
tools of of figure out what the next
thing, you know, might be or like, you
know, agentic tools. So, there might be
like as as always with software but
there might be like composable layers of
tools. And those you can call them now
from here it's like it's an interface
question. And maybe maybe there is a
case of, you know, a developer at Cloud
Code at their terminal. Maybe there's a
case of like a headless, you know, when
an incident gets called something
automatically ran.
And I think for both of those
it probably probably doesn't really
matter if it's a like for the first one
clearly it's wherever the user was. And
so if they're in cloud codes then then
you should integrate as a tool. The
middle layer probably can run either
way, right? You can invoke a headless
cloud codes to sort of have whatever the
relevant kind of MCP tools to do the
analysis.
But but really it's your sort of agentic
process of it so it just just as well
run in your system. But but the other
part is if you're really in a hey I'm
troubleshooting this has the review
exercise of like how do I collaborate
with the AI
over here. And that's the part that's
I guess we're sort of most shaping
at the moment. It reminds me a bit of
I had a conversation here with with
Merill the CEO and founder of
of Graphite.
And we talked about reviews and like to
some extent I think code review as it is
done today my opinion a lot of that is
is would be a bit nonsensical in the
sense that you you want the same
reviews, the same questions to happen
before. But review as an action of like
reviewing the results of
the AI's kind of coding is is probably
more fundamental than ever and will kind
of continue to grow in importance. And
so figuring out the right UX, what is it
that you are reviewing, how is it that
you're collaborating is um
is kind of an interesting question to to
sort out. Does that sound aligned?
Absolutely. I also think for us it's an
existential question, right?
Because if it turns out that the
user will use observability in other
tools
I think then we are just a database,
Right. and then will mean that it's a
race to the bottom in terms of pricing
and so the value then is not generated
anymore in our tool, it's generated in
cursor or any other SRE agent tool or
whatever. So for us it's really
existential to see, okay, how can we
provide more value Yeah. inside of our
tool than you get in a cursor or in an
AI AI SRE agent because if we can't
provide more value, I think it is it is
an existential threat, right? Because at
the end people will pay for the value
not for the data. And if the value is
somewhere else generated, then we will
at the end be a database, right? And
then it it it's not good. So, that's
really how I think about it. So, for me
it's really about, okay, if I can create
this interaction with the user and can
provide real value
uh that's that's awesome, right? And
also, I have to say you you probably
know, but if you if you look at large
organizations,
we have hundreds of users registering
for observability, but only a fraction
of them are really using it. Right.
>> Because you need to kind of be an expert
to do troubleshooting service. So, I
think we have the chance with agentic AI
to enable
almost 100% of the users to get value
out of it because it can help you
following uh the right actions inside of
the tool and it can guide you. So, I
think that's that's really
powerful. And then you get more value,
right? Because if 100% of the users can
get and trouble they
>> self-service and they can build those.
And the the the the most clear
demonstrations of AI productivity in in
sort of the the entire software
development life cycle, including
observability, are cases where you used
to have a dependence on another team
Yeah.
>> and you didn't anymore, right? Or in
general, where you skip a whole step.
Some of it is, you know, a a product or
a support or someone else logs a bug and
a background agent, you know, figures
out and you only meet the solution at
the pull request. Maybe at some point
even that gets auto-resolved. So, that's
an example. Sometimes it's a
uh something that needed to go from the
back end team to the front end team and
then get deployed, but now one of those
teams can take it all the way. So, you
know, it a And so, I think the the
opportunity that you're describing here
makes a lot of sense, which is the more
self-sufficient, the more sort of single
owner can take it all the way through,
uh the more the more productivity you
get. And And now the question becomes
just like what's the what's the scope of
the product and what value do you get
from from which Exactly. And there's a
second We We just talked about the root
cause analysis, but there is a set of
other issues, which I call is it's
mostly removing toil, right? It's
removing tasks that you really don't
like, right? And as a simple example is
dashboards, building dashboards for a
service,
and then you have an update in your
service, and you you have that service
on 50 dashboards, and now you have to
update all these 50 dashboards manually
to have that new metric on it, right?
And um I think that's where AI is also
super powerful, right? It It can create
and suggest dashboards for a problem or
service. It can automatically update
those dashboards. Same for alerts,
right? You have alert rules, something
changes, and you need to update all
these alert rules, right? And I think
that's where we also we created agents
that help you create, update dashboards,
create, update alerts. Yeah. Um
And And do those things, right? I think
that makes a ton of sense. Yeah. And And
And And another big point is
uh adding more context.
And that means we are adding other data
sources to observability
to understand the context better of a
problem. As an example, we connect to
linear and Jira, or we connect to your
notion.
And by doing that, we can actually see,
oh, well, maybe there was I have a
database issue with the with the schema.
Maybe there was a task that updated the
schema,
>> and I can correlate it to it, right? Or
maybe there is a documentation in notion
with the schema update, which I can use
and pinpoint user to it. Or I can use
the code, the connection to GitHub, to
pinpoint to uh a change in the code,
etc., right? I think adding more context
is also very important
now because the agents can can use that
context to create better answers. Yeah.
And so this And this comes back to the
root cause analysis. That agent might
come along and and figure it out, but
you have to
relate, like give it access and relate
it to it. And I guess organizationally,
one of the one of the challenges that I
hear talking to the enterprise side of
it, you know, talking to the companies
using these different tools is is sort
of this infinite mesh of connectivity
between all these different tools. Like
the number of tools I need to connect to
my linear, I need to connect. And then
there's going to be another subset of
tool that might want to connect to Dash
0 as a source of information. I want to
read something about the logs because, I
don't know, I'm writing code and I want
to get that information doing it and all
this sort of cross-pollination of it.
And so it's interesting.
I don't know what your view is, you
know, at at Tessal, we
we more and more sort of think about
context as a as a core competency that's
a bit agent agnostic. And so there are
statements about your system, statements
about your knowledge, your practices,
how a system should operate, but also
like what should your code do and what
are your coding best practices and you
know,
how to use a certain library. And all of
those things right now are being derived
or sort of intelligently, AI-powered,
assessed, and extracted out of systems
by so many different agents as we all
figure out, you know, what's going on.
And
and and we we kind of store them inside.
I guess how do you think about
the challenge of over there clearly is
is
like where do we go, right? Are you
going to curate context in 20 different
spots or do you want to curate them in
some central
central environment? And so I guess my
my question back maybe to the
existential thing as well is what what
do you think is is the core of
observability knowledge? You know, if if
the coding side revolves around the code
or maybe the product functionality, like
an observability
you you're a database, but what's the uh
you know, what's the most important
long-term insight or sort of knowledge
that you think lives in operations and
not earlier in the system? That I don't
know if that makes sense. No, makes
total sense. I think uh I I'm just not
sure if I have a 100% of the answer to
that right now, but uh I think the
question makes total sense. And I do
think there are multiple things, right?
Uh one is, as we discussed, the tools
that you provide. And that can be a lot
of
uh knowledge and and and context
already, right? How do you figure out
what are anomalies and traces and and
how do you figure out these uh tags or
>> Right. Thing I wanted to ask a question,
you know,
>> How to ask the questions, yeah? Uh I
think also there will be a lot of
knowledge about how do you evaluate
models and and so the evaluations that
you have and how do you essentially make
sure that uh the root cause analysis
does what you think it should do, right?
And also giving some guidance. But there
are there are more and more these to-do
lists that you give, so that it that the
workflow is not every time
uh uh
different, but you have the knowledge if
there's a certain type of problem, how
to do the analysis, right? And which
step you should follow on on the on the
wider scope. I think that's something.
And then I think last but not least, it
is really the user experience.
The the the way you integrate the agents
into
a collaborative mode, right? Basically
coming from a single-player mode also to
a multiplayer mode where at the end of
the day, if you troubleshoot, you
normally have these war rooms, right?
And and multiple uh people are are
working on that problem. And agents are
now
part of the war room, right? Yeah. You
maybe have one or two three agents
working with you in parallel,
investigating things, giving you
information. That information is then
processed by user. You give more context
to the agent. And and that way you can
I I think that will be a big part of it,
right?
Who figures out Yeah.
>> the best user experience, the best way
of doing it.
And to your last question, I like the
idea to have that knowledge some
somewhere
persisted, right? About a system, about
certain things, how it works.
I don't know we would be the system. I I
also like the idea that it should be a
centralized uh
I mean, you had these enterprise
architecture management tools
Yeah.
>> before, right? Where you had the whole
system documented or or should document
your whole landscape and and give hints.
I think
I can see why you would have a lot of
that context into a centralized tool
where all the agents can access and get
some
understanding of how how things work and
how they are configured, rules, etc. I
think that makes sense, right? The The
enterprise architecture management tool
for agents, right? That Yeah. that has
has it in a way that agents can work
with it and understand it and understand
certain things. I think makes sense.
Yeah. Yeah, I think
it's it's a good analogy. It's like so
many things when you're when you're
sufficiently old like us, you know, you
sort of see the
you know, see see a bunch of these you
know, a whole bunch of like practices
that were
were good practices. They were just too
hard to maintain at pace and at scale.
And now with agents maybe we we do
those. And so those sort of central
systems of record
well well attuned for consumption. We'll
touch on consumption by whom in a sec.
Is
is it an opportunity, you know, to to
build on? When when I started my career,
I worked for IBM, and we had we had a
different set of documents we had to
maintain
in every project. And one of them I
really loved it was a document called
architectural decisions.
And essentially whenever you did a
decision, I used this and that framework
or whatever, you had to document it and
explain why. Right? Because whenever you
had a new team member join the team
they ask you why why did you use this
framework? Doesn't make sense, right?
You can pinpoint them to the document
because there was actually reason for
it. And once you read it, you you
understand. I think that's also would be
good for agents, right? If they come in
and say, "Oh, why did you do this and
that?" But maybe there's a reason for it
the agent cannot understand. And so you
should have some sort of kind of
categorized
Yeah. knowledge
Yeah. for those agents, right?
>> Yeah. And curated and in the place that
you can also choose to change it over
time on it. And And then on top of that
what we see is, you know, you you write
it down, but not all agents listen the
same. Uh and so you you need to um I I
guess that as I think about AI native, I
think AI native is is primarily about
delegating
work to AI and or tasks on it. And I
think when you think about delegation,
the sort of the really the two things
when you think about the human analogy
that you need to do is, okay, did you
did you equip, you know, the the entity
that you're delegating to with enough
information that it's sort of plausible
that they will get it done. Right? Like
what is your intent? What is the
knowledge around the system? So what
information is available to them? And
then two is how would you verify their
work? And so to me that's basically
context and and evals.
So those are like the two. So you have
to have some means the evals are clearly
not going to be comprehensive just like
with humans, you know, you're not going
to know how to verify every single task
that your employee did because then like
sort of pointless
to to have them. But you do need to sort
of spot check, I guess, and sort of
assess it. And so with the agents like,
here's the information. Did you Did you
listen? Did you Is this a Did you Did
you understand? Right?
You can't force them to listen, but
understanding is depends on the the
model.
So So let's uh let's maybe talk a little
bit about the human side. And to start
that, you know, we you know, if I talk
about AI native, this was like a little
bit of my definition. Uh when we spoke
about what is an AI native product, a
lot of a lot of your focus was on this
notion of building agent first. And so
how do you how do you think about the
future of your product in terms of its
primary constituency? You know, is it
agents or humans? How do you delineate
the two? Yeah, the way the way we do now
design of our product is really that we
the we think of everything first of in
the perspective of an AI agent.
Right? And also what an AI agent could
probably do with that information and
how we can make life easier for the user
then, right? So
that's
probably the most important things for
for us at the moment is really always
say, "Okay, can an agent do that work?
How would that look like? And how would
that information feed back to the user
that it's understandable? And also I
would call it traceable, right? So So I
I think for us essentially in
observability, one of the most important
thing we got from our users is that they
want to understand why the AI agent has
come to a certain conclusion. And you
really want to follow it, right? And if
we say, "Yeah, the the problem is is
here, the database."
Then often the question is, "Oh, why did
you come up with that conclusion?"
Right? And then you want to follow the
steps essentially how the agent was
getting there. So it's always about,
"Okay, what can the agent do? And how do
we make that
understandable to the user? And where
are the interaction points of the user
with that agent?" Right? So but it's not
anymore that we say we built a tool
where the user is the prime primary
Yeah. basically interaction point with
with us. We think that the agent is the
primary action point now. Yeah. It
should do most of the work and the user
should just interact with the agent at
points where the user has the knowledge
uh uh to to make make the agent better,
right? So, the interface, I guess
another way to say this is uh you think
the primary UX for the user for the user
will be to to interact with the agent.
Uh and Yes. And so, the there's like a
layer uh of of functionality that is
aimed quite heavily at the agent uh to
to achieve this. And then for the user,
you have to solve for a different
problem. Uh and And I guess some things
go away. I don't know. Is there an
example that jumps to mind of like
uh how this I guess kind of led you to
build something a little bit differently
or uh
Let's
let's let's think of a very simple
thing, a dashboard, right? For a
service. So, you have a service payment
service and a dashboard. It used to be
the normal thing is you put on the red
metrics where you show how many calls do
you have to that service, what was the
response time, how many errors did you
have. And I think today, the primary
information we give you on a service is
is a textual description of the status
of the service.
It would tell you uh your your service
is operating fine. It uh it it is in the
in the range of the performance of the
last 30 days, but we found two errors
which came up recently that we haven't
seen before which are suspicious. And
then you say, "Okay, let's investigate
them." And then from there So, you're
not looking at charts or anything
anymore. You're looking at that. And
then the next thing is that you interact
with the agent. You say, "Okay,
investigate those problems for me." And
so, now it jumps to the let's say to the
trace view and analyzes already set all
the context, right? It it it has uh uh
filtered down to exactly those problems.
It will show you the right information,
the context. And And now the next thing
is it just Look at here, it's only for
that customer uh in in that scenario.
And And here we go, right? So, the the
steps are all very simple.
Uh you get all the context. Product
design, it's not any more about charts,
numbers, Yeah. uh and those things
because the agent will do the work for
you to look at those charts essentially.
Yeah.
>> And And give you a summary of the things
that are important for you to look at.
Yeah. And And we I
I really like that, and I think it it
comes back to the first principles of
like, why did we have the chart in the
first place? Well, the the the the the
task wasn't give me a chart. The task
really was, I want to understand what
the status of my service is.
Uh and charts are
are just the way we got used to
uh looking at them.
And by the way, charts are good for
users, not good for agents, right?
That's an interesting thing also, right?
We We created charts because we as
humans, we are really good at looking at
a chart and seeing a spike,
right? Right. Where Where the agent will
actually look at the underlying data and
do a deep analysis of the data, but we
cannot look at 5,000 data points and
then see the We don't see the spike in
5,000 data points, right? That's not how
our brain works. We We look at charts.
So, but that's a good point, right? An
agent doesn't need charts anymore. The
charts are just for the user. Yeah. And
essentially, we created the chart for
the user to pinpoint an anomaly. Yeah.
So, now when the agent already tells
you, "I found an anomaly. Do you want me
to investigate it?" The the charts gets
useless, right? Because you don't you
don't need it anymore. But Yeah.
>> how I think we have to rethink Yeah. The
first
>> first principles. Why Why have you
started with it? And And we normally
build the user experience to the
weaknesses of the human brain, right?
Yeah.
>> And
And now we can optimize it because the
agent can do the heavy work, right? The
heavy lifting. And and and we just
follow follow it, right? I I I love that
but also I love how it it actually sort
of touches both sides of the weaknesses
and strengths, right? You're saying
one part is there's an opportunity to
give a user a human user better answer
than a chart, you know, here's the
actual conclusion of the chart. But also
that if you if you work from outside and
you're trying to have the agents just
rely on the information that is
available to to the to the human, it
would actually do a worse job because
the agents are not as good at at
understanding the the charts as as
humans.
So I like I I I love that sort of
analogy and example and I guess the the
next question will be on well,
who who is this for and how does it
maybe change the sort of the profile of
the individual cuz you're already
alluding to you know, today there's a
certain level of expertise for people
that really truly operate the DevOps
dashboards. So some of that is also
getting down to like contextualizing I
guess the answer to people with
different companies just like as a as a
human you'd explain you'd use different
words to explain the same scenario to
people with different level of
proficiency. I mean normally if
troubleshooting came down to a few
people in the organization who have a
very
and one they need a very broad
understanding of the overall system.
Yeah. Cuz a lot of developers and and
people have only a deep understanding of
their service but not if you have a
microservice environment with a thousand
services, there are only a few people
who really understand how everything
works together. Yeah. And normally in
troubleshooting scenarios you need that
understanding to narrow down
where to look at, right? Right. What
could be the problem because I always
say or
if if there is a big problem,
systems normally look like a Christmas
tree because everything is blinking,
right? Because everything is somehow
connected. So, everything is red and
then it doesn't help anymore because if
everything is red, you still don't know
where it's coming from, right? And then
you need this expert knowledge of people
say, "Yeah, but it's probably here
because I know there's this database
that's connected to everything else."
And Yeah. And I think that's why you
only have these power users being really
effective difference of observability
because you need that understanding,
right? And I think that's where the
agent comes in because agents are good
at understanding the wider scope and
narrowing it down. And now we can enable
everyone to
basically having that knowledge
about the overall system because the
agent can give you that context, Right.
Yeah. And and now everyone can
troubleshoot. Uh I'm not saying that we
are already there yet, but I think the
ultimate goal would be to enable every
developer or every SRE, everyone who who
needs to have that knowledge
uh uh troubleshooting and understanding
the system quickly, right? Right. Yeah.
Uh with without having that as expert
knowledge or new people coming in,
right? Which is also a problem in
enterprises. Now Now these two people
who have the knowledge leave the
company. Yeah. Yeah. And as we all know,
it's normally not documented in Notion,
Confluence, or somewhere. It's in the
head of the of the people.
And now that knowledge is gone, right?
And and
And so this is and and this to me comes
back to that sort of is really
the separation between intelligence and
knowledge, right? And so
>> Yeah. so you want to enable
intelligence. The agents kind of give
you some intelligence. You can look at a
lot of logs. You can find the spikes.
You can go. You can search. You can find
related information. But then there's
also knowledge of what is the system,
what is
what have been the sort of the past
incidents that we've had so that you
know there's always that sort of thing
database you know, that's sort of in the
corner.
Uh, you know how do you build those? Um,
and I I think the I think one of the
challenges that what people conflate
uh, intelligence and knowledge. And you
know, like I I sometimes say it's like
assume intelligence not mind reading,
you know, like there's no
uh, you know, they can be super
intelligent, but if you do not equip
them with knowledge, it's anywhere
between the set up to failure to just
highly inefficient. Like every time
they're going to have to uh, to learn
that.
I'm curious about the uh, the people
side. So maybe like as a bit of a
closing as we kind of run out of time
here.
Uh, uh, so so this is all good and well
and it's the future. Maybe bringing it
down to today, what is what is the
journey that you're seeing customers or
walking customers through in terms of
adopting this approach? Cuz a a bunch of
this
there's a fair bit of change uh,
involved in what you've described and
people don't always like change. And
also there's limitations of the
technology uh, today. So it can't quite
do uh, everything amazingly yet. I would
say first of all, it's it's
it's really changing the way users work.
There was a public statement by the CIO
of The Telegraph in London. He He made
it actually on LinkedIn. He said that
the Sero and Agent Zero are changing the
way they do incident the playbook for
incident resolution are changing because
now
the first place is to ask the AI
and not anymore going through the list
of steps to do to to troubleshoot. And
it's I I think so. So the agents are
already changing the way we do incident
resolution etc. because they are super
helpful, right? Probably also how
uh, according agents are changing the
way we code. We probably first ask an
agent to do a suggestion and then we
iterate with it or how we do a post on
LinkedIn first ask Gemini or whatever,
right? So
uh, I think that's already happening uh,
for sure.
Um, what I would say today is that it's
really a learning curve on both sides,
right? I mean, we have a chat interface
and we, for example, we also look
heavily on what the users are asking our
system, right? Because it's the first
time that we is essentially user can do
something with the system that we
haven't designed for them, right?
Uh, normally you can only use
functionality that you have literally
designed in the user experience, but now
they can ask questions like, oh, give me
a usage report of the dashboards. We we
never thought about this and actually
turns out that the agent can answer that
question. So, we now know, oh, actually
users are interested in usage of
dashboards.
>> Right. So, we get feedback through that
interface also to understand what kind
of functionality we should bake into the
tool, right? Because the the the tool
today is it's probably how how ChatGPT
when they started, they saw people are
asking coding questions and then they
you you could see, oh, maybe we build
something like the coding agents, right?
It's it's it's a use case. And so, that
we see that, too. But, at the moment, I
think it's a
it's it's learning on both sides, right?
It's what works, what doesn't work, how
does it change my
my procedures, my playbooks, right? I we
see customers already changing their
playbooks on incident resolution, but I
think over time it it it will become an
integral part of observability. I think
even today you
we can't imagine anymore having
observability without AI. Yeah. Yeah,
no, I I I love that and I guess it's a
it's an extreme version of what we're
doing in general when you're building a
product, you should listen to your
users. But, because the because you're
providing users with with an interface
that is much closer to what they would
say to a support person or sort of to
your to your rep, right? Or to to an
engineer on the team,
than the free form version of it. It's
you know, you don't have to like
decipher what they meant from the clicks
on the
the the page or the dashboard they
created. You're getting a more verbatim
version of like this is the question I
had. Can you Can you answer it, right?
Or can you provide that?
>> Yeah, especially if you never had this
option before, right? You could never
click on it. You would never get that
answer without talking to the customer,
right?
>> Right. Yeah, absolutely.
So, I think
I
excited to see this evolve. I mean, I
find the world of DevOps
in general is is like a bit cautious
around AI and observability feels is
like the pioneering part of it because
it has a lot of data analysis and a lot
of like
a lot of toil
to that, you know, to kind of take away.
So, it's exciting to sort of see
Agent Zero and and in general kind of a
kind of AI native approaches and sort of
the changes of the practices and I'm
very sort of keen to see that. I'm
curious about the sort of the closing of
the loop and we'll see that as I guess
as the systems become more reliable.
So, definitely will be kind of in a
close in tracking. Before I let you go
here though, I want to ask one kind of a
personal question that I'd like to ask
many of the guests here.
Typically, I would ask well, if you had
a son that, you know, was going to
university, would you recommend that
they go take computer science? And when
we're talking, it's like it turns out
you have a son that is just started sort
of
studying. So, I guess
how do you think about kind of the
career path in sort of software
engineering today? You know, do
I guess kind of it sounds like you still
think it's a good idea to go into a
computer science degree today, you know,
how do you think where where do you
think this is headed?
And what's a good thing for someone to
do today, right? If they're sort of
early in their career.
I mean, I definitely recommended it to
my son and the reason for it is that I
think that the main thing you get
trained doing a computer science or
engineering
study is to trains your brain
in understanding problems, math, etc.,
right? I mean,
I I I was a coding geek since I was a
child, right? So, I learned coding
myself, not at university. For I studied
computer science, but what you learn
there is you learn to solve hard
mathematical problems, physics, etc. And
I think that will not go away, right? I
think having a brain that helps you
analyze problems and and structure
things, I think that's still really
relevant and
I just think he should do that to get
that basic training
and then figure out what he wants to do.
And he's actually he loves hardware and
I think that's a very interesting yeah,
spot in the future, right? Robots,
drones, all these things are uh also a
very interesting combination with AI and
and software. So
yeah, I I
I think it's it's still relevant. Yeah.
I think it's a it's a super interesting
and I get different rules on it and I
I absolutely agree around the
deal with hard problems, you know, like
learn to overcome adversity to begin
with. It's just a hard degree to get
through and it's like life lessons of
that. Hopefully have some good teachers
who learn how to tackle problems.
I guess maybe what I would add is like I
think the importance as it as it stands
if you go to a computer science degree,
you come out if you didn't do any
programming on the side, you're probably
not a very good programmer, you know, by
that time, you know, like you're not a
but so you learn a lot. You need to
learn alongside the degree and I think
that is probably more important than
ever cuz I think where I put very little
faith is in the universities ability to
adapt anywhere near fast enough to teach
the students the the knowledge part
of of what they need from an AI
perspective in in kind of the AI era. So
I guess the sort of the emphasis there
is
you know, do that but then you know,
alongside the degree learn who's that
zero or
>> [laughter]
>> like I don't know like get some
experience with some sort of agentic
development tools to uh Absolutely.
Yeah. I agree.
Uh Mirko, thanks a lot for coming on to
the show and sharing these insights and
looking forward to see the the future of
observability
in this AI era.
Thank you. It was nice being on your
show here.
And thanks everyone for tuning back in
and I hope you join us for the next one.